<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="ch-Matrices">
    <title>Matrices and their operations</title>
        <objectives>
        <ol type="1">
            <li><p>Define a <em>matrix</em> and discuss the implementation of a matrix class.</p></li>
            <li><p>Discuss the algebraic operations of scalar multiplication and addition of matrices.</p></li>
            <li><p>Discuss the algorithm for matrix multiplication.</p></li>
            <li><p>Implement a minimal matrix class.</p></li>
        </ol>
    </objectives>

    <introduction>
        <title>What is a matrix?</title>
        <p>
            A <em>matrix</em> is a rectangular grid numerical elements. For instance, and by way of demonstrating the form we will use to write a matrix,
            <me>
                A=\begin{bmatrix}
                <![CDATA[ \pi & e & 6.2 \\]]>
                <![CDATA[ \frac13 & 7 & -42]]>
                \end{bmatrix}
            </me>
            and
            <me>
                B = \begin{bmatrix}
                <![CDATA[1 & 0 & 0 & 0 \\]]>
                <![CDATA[0 & 1 & 0 & 0 \\]]>
                <![CDATA[0 & 0 & 1 & 0 \\]]>
                <![CDATA[0 & 0 & 0 & 1]]>
                \end{bmatrix}
            </me>
            are matrices. Neither
            <me>
                C = \begin{bmatrix}
                <![CDATA[5 & 8 \\]]>
                <![CDATA[2 & 3 & 0 ]]>
                \end{bmatrix}
            </me>
            nor
            <me>
                D = \begin{bmatrix}
                <![CDATA[\text{Eric} & \text{John}\\]]>
                <![CDATA[\text{Graham} & \text{Terry}]]>
                \end{bmatrix}
            </me>
            are matrices, the first because it is non-rectangular and the second because the names of members of Monty Python are not numbers.
        </p>
        <p>
            We will use this chapter to build a Sage class <c>aam_Matrix</c> representing mathematical matrices, and refine it in further chapters.
        </p>
        
    </introduction>
    <!--<xi:include  href="section5_8x.xml" />-->
    <xi:include  href="sec-matrices-defn.xml" />
    <!--<xi:include  href="section5_2.xml" />-->
    <xi:include  href="sec-matrices-ops.xml" />
    <xi:include  href="sec-matrices-mult.xml" />
    
    <conclusion>
        <title>A formal definition of a matrix</title>
        <p>
            To formally define a matrix requires a notion of a <em>field</em>, which is a particularly strong algebraic object. The model of a field is the set of rational numbers with the operations of addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division by nonzero numbers. Once the <em>field axioms</em> are satisfied for a particular set, there are a further set of axioms which define a <em>vector space</em> over the field. The behavior of matrices with elements from a given field is directly tied to the concept of a <em>linear transformation</em> of a vector space over that field. For an online introduction to matrix theory, vector space theory, and linear algebra, see the online beta version of Dr. Rob Beezer's <url href='http://linear.ups.edu/fcla/index.html' > First Course in Linear Algebra</url>. For the brief, technical definition, see <xref ref="formal-vectorspace" autoname="title" />.
        </p>
    </conclusion>
</chapter>
