<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" >
    <title>Shortest Paths</title>


    <objectives>
        <ol type="1">
            <li><p>Discuss the shortest path problem.</p></li>
            <li><p>Explain Dijkstra's shortest path algorithm.</p></li>
            <li><p>Implement Dijkstra's algorithm.</p></li>
        </ol>
    </objectives>

    <introduction>
        <title>Erd&#337;s Number</title>
        <p>
            The mathematician Paul Erd&#337;s is renowned for having been one of the most prolific mathematicians of the 20th century, as well as one of the most social: he wrote papers with more than 500 collaborators over his career. Due to his frequent collaborations, one of his coauthors assigned to Paul an <q>Erd&#337;s number</q> of 0, for being Paul Erd&#337;s. Each of Erd&#337;s's coauthors were assigned an Erd&#337;s number of 1. Their coauthors who did not coauthor with Erd&#337;s were assigned an Erd&#337;s number of 2, and so on.
        </p>

        <p>
            This builds a <em>rooted collaboration graph</em>: a graph whose vertices are mathematicians and edges are coauthorship on a paper, with a special <em>root vertex</em> designated as Paul Erd&#337;s. The distance in this graph is the length of a shortest path between vertices. The question then is how to determine a shortest path.
        </p>

        <p>
            While this problem is described in terms of something lighthearted, shortest paths are important in other mediums as well. In fact, one of the largest graphs under current study is the Facebook graph! If a transmission of a message in a network is more likely to have errors introduced with each subsequent connection traversed, it is important to minimize the number of transmissions. With a little creativity, the shortest path problem can be applied to hyperspace routing for a particular type of fictional faster-than-light travel.
        </p>
    </introduction>

    <!--xi:include  href="section13_1.xml" /-->
    <xi:include  href="section13_2.xml" />
    <xi:include  href="section13_3.xml" />
</chapter>
