<section xml:id="s-SB-CC">
    <title>CoCalc</title>
        <p>
            The best practical way to learn Sage is to get a CoCalc account and just dig into using Sage. A good practice for using this text as an online ebook is to have CoCalc open in a separate browser window and start a new worksheet for each major division of the book. All your <q>try it out</q> work will then be saved for you to go back and look at what you did, with all the versions of changes logged.
        </p>
        <p>
            We're going to extensively discuss actual code in these notes, so let's determine some conventions. 
        </p>
        <convention xml:id="conv-inlinecode" number="none"> 
            <p>Text which appears <c>like this</c> will hereafter always be one of two things: Sage (or Python) code, or a filename. On the other hand, <url><c>http://cocalc.com</c></url> is a web address.</p>
        </convention>
        <convention xml:id="conv-blockcode">>
            <p>
                More serious code will occur offset in a block. There are two kinds: a <term>program listings</term>, and an <term>executable Sage cell</term>. Here's what a program listing will look like:
            </p>
            <listing>
                <program>
                    <input>
                        example code
                        more example code
                        even more example code
                    </input>
                </program>
                <caption>
                    This is a <em>program listing</em>, which cannot be executed can be easily copied and pasted.
                </caption>
            </listing>
            <p>
                On the other hand, here's an executable Sage Cell.
            </p>
            <sage>
                <input>
                    print "This is an example of an executable Sage Cell."
                </input>
                <output>
                    This is an example of an executable SageCell.
                </output>
            </sage>
            <p>
                The main reason for using each of these is that in the case of a program listing, you are encouraged to copy the listing into a different window (hopefully running CoCalc) and execute the code. This will allow you to modify and retain modifications to the code. A simple SageCell, on the other hand, is all that is necessary to demonstrate a practical programming feature.
            </p>
        </convention>
</section>