<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="s-W-TB">
    <title>Organization of the text</title>
    <introduction>
        <p>
            The book is divided into chapters, each of which centers around the project at the end of the chapter; the goal is that each chapter will be covered in a regular week of classes. The intention is that the vast majority of people reading the book will do so in the browser as a webpage, in which case each section of a chapter is its own page. Errors in the online web version of the book will be caught regularly, corrected, and pushed out to Github; see <xref ref="AAM-BM-AR" text="auto"/>.
        </p>
    </introduction>
    <subsection xml:id="ss-W-TB-NT">
        <title>Notation and terminology</title>
        <p>
            There are a few common styles of text you'll read in this book which bear explanation:
            <table>
                <title>Meaning of text styles</title>
                <tabular top="major" bottom="none">
                    <col halign="left" />
                    <col halign="left" width="40%"/>
                    <row bottom="medium">
                        <cell> Style </cell>
                        <cell> Meaning </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> <url href="http://math.uttyler.edu/sjgraves/aam/" /> </cell>
                        <cell> <p>A URL or other link. This one is to the live online version of this book.</p> </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> <c>print</c> </cell>
                        <cell> inline code, or a filename </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> <term>terminology</term> </cell>
                        <cell> the first use of a technical term </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> <em>emphasized text</em> </cell>
                        <cell> text being used emphatically! </cell>
                    </row>
<!--                     <row>
                        <cell> <tt>plain text</tt> </cell>
                        <cell> <p>unformatted text, generally meant to be a string of input</p> </cell>
                    </row> -->
                </tabular>
            </table>
        </p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection xml:id="ss-W-TB-CRQE">
        <title>Checkpoints, reading questions, and exercises</title>
        <p>
            The intention in the current revision of the text is to include many questions of several types. These different types serve different needs.
        </p>
        <p>
            The first type of exercise will be the <term>checkpoint</term>. Checkpoints will be interspersed throughout the body of the text and serve exactly as what they are called: points at which to check to see that you have understood the most recent discussion. 
        </p>
        <exercise>
            <title>A first checkpoint!</title>
            <p>
                What should you do when you reach a checkpoint?
            </p>
        </exercise>
        <p>
            At the end of each Section should be a block of <term>reading questions</term>. The goal of these is to ensure you're keeping up with the text and reading carefully. If you read a reading question and feel incapable of answering it without referring back to the text at least once, this is an indication that you should pause in answering questions to go back and reread the section carefully.
        </p>
        <p>
            Finally, at the end of each chapter will be a section of <term>exercises</term>. These will range in difficulty and should remind you of the types of exercises you've seen in textbooks in the past.
        </p>
        <warning xml:id="warn_exercises">
            <title>Exercise is good for you</title>
            <p>
            Mathematical exercises serve much the same purpose as physical exercises: they both build strength in their respective area and help you to maintain strength you already have. Any exercises included in the text are solely included for the benefit of the reader <mdash/> the author can already solve them. <em>If you ignore exercises and only attempt work that is collected for a grade, you miss the purpose of education.</em>
            </p>
        </warning>
    </subsection>
    <subsection xml:id="ss-W-TB-P">
        <title>Projects</title>
        <p>
            The central feature of the redesign of the text is to orient all content around chapter-level projects. These should be challenging but solvable using the content of the textbook, and lectures on course material should be a sort of <q>artistic accompaniment</q> to the text.
        </p>
    </subsection>
    <conclusion>
        <title>A philosophy</title>
        <p>
            There are many good strategies for effective thinking. The goal of this text is to help you think effectively about algorithms and computationally solving interesting mathematical problems. Paraphrasing a broad strategy from Burger and Starbird's <pubtitle>The 5 Elements of Effective Thinking</pubtitle>, we should:
        </p>
        <ol>
            <li>Understand the fundamentals.</li>
            <li>Make mistakes in order to learn.</li>
            <li>Ask basic questions challenging what we know.</li>
            <li>Follow the flow of ideas.</li>
            <li>Change what we're doing to adapt and do <em>better</em>.</li>
        </ol>
        <p>
            As a final thought, consider the following:
        </p>
        <blockquote>
            <p>If a thing is worth doing, it is worth doing badly.</p>
            <attribution>G. K. Chesterton, in <pubtitle>What's Wrong with the World</pubtitle></attribution>
        </blockquote>
        <p>
            In this often-repeated quote, Chesterton was specifically discussing hobbies and recreational activities, but there is a great deal of truth in the quote when applied to <q>important</q> activities as well. Specifically, if a thing is worth doing, it's worth doing badly long enough to get it right.
<!--             As an organizational philosophy for the course, let's think about ideas as follows:
 -->
        </p>
    </conclusion>
    <reading-questions>
        <exercise>
            <statement>
                What are the three different types of exercises used in this text?
            </statement>
            <answer>
                Checkpoints, reading questions (like this one!) and exercises.
            </answer>
        </exercise>
        <exercise>
            <statement>
                What is the central design feature of the text?
            </statement>
            <answer>
                Everything should be oriented around chapter-level projects. Isn't this fun?
            </answer>
        </exercise>
    </reading-questions>
</section>
