<section xml:id="sec-Permutations-Groups">
    <title>Permutation groups</title>
    <p>
        Since permutations of a set <m>A</m> are bijections from <m>A</m> to <m>A</m>, they can be composed.
    </p>

    <theorem>
        <statement>
            <p>
                Suppose <m>\sigma,\tau\in S_A</m> for some set <m>A</m>. Then the composition of <m>\tau</m> after <m>\sigma</m> is a permutation <m>\tau\circ\sigma:A\to A</m> defined by
                <me>
                    (\tau\circ\sigma)(a) = \tau(\sigma(a))
                </me>
                for each <m>a\in A</m>. Moreover, the composition symbol <m>\circ</m> will be suppressed, and we will write <m>\tau\sigma</m> as a product rather than a composition<fn>This is familiar: think of <m>f(x) = \arctan\cos(x)</m>.</fn>.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </theorem>

    <p>
        Two-line notation makes calculating the composition of permutations uncomplicated, if the permutations are stacked in the correct order.
    </p>

    <remark>
        <title>Two-line permutation product diagrams</title>
        <statement>
            <p>
                Consider the permutations
                <md>
                    <mrow>
                        g \amp = \verb|10 9 5 7 8 6 2 3 4 1|
                    </mrow>
                    <intertext>and</intertext>
                    <mrow>
                        h \amp = \verb|8 1 5 9 4 6 7 3 10 2|.
                    </mrow>
                </md>
                We can easily determine the effect of the product <m>hg(2)</m> by following the output of <m>g(2)</m> through <m>h</m>, as depicted by the blue line in the figure below.
                <figure>
                    <image source='./images/perm_prod_ex1.svg' />
                    <caption>The product <m>hg</m> applied to 2.</caption>
                </figure>
                If each possible such arrow is followed, the result can be tabulated in the two-line notation for <m>\sigma_2\sigma_1</m>,
                <me>
                    hg = \begin{bmatrix}
                    1 \amp 2 \amp 3 \amp 4 \amp 5 \amp 6 \amp 7 \amp 8 \amp 9 \amp 10 \\
                    3 \amp 10 \amp 8 \amp 4 \amp 7 \amp 6 \amp 2 \amp 5 \amp 1 \amp 9
                    \end{bmatrix}.
                </me>
            </p>
            <p>
                As a memory aid the product <m>hg</m> should be read as <q><m>h</m> of <m>g</m>,</q> rather than <q><m>h</m> times <m>g</m>,</q> much as with fractions: <m>\frac32(15)</m> can be read as <q>three halves of fifteen.</q>
            </p>
        </statement>
    </remark>
    <p>
        Having defined multiplication of permutations, it is natural to consider whether there is a <em>multiplicative identity</em>.
    </p>
    <theorem>
        <statement>
            <p>
                Suppose <m>A</m> is a set, and let <m>e_A:A\to A</m> be the function such that <m>e_A(a)=a</m> for each <m>a\in A</m>. Then <m>e_A</m> is the <term>identity permutation on <m>A</m></term>. When the set <m>A</m> being permuted is clear by context, the identity permutation will simply be denoted <m>e</m>.
            </p>
            <p>
                The identity permutation <m>e_A</m> is the unique permutation such that <m>e_A\sigma=\sigma=\sigma e_A</m> for every permutation <m>\sigma</m>.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </theorem>

    <p>
        Having an identity, another natural question to ask is whether each permutation has an inverse; we know from calculus that all injective functions are invertible!
    </p>

    <theorem>
        <statement>
            <p>
                Suppose <m>\sigma\in S_A</m>. Then there is a unique <term>inverse</term> for <m>\sigma</m>, denoted <m>\sigma^{-1}</m>, such that <m>\sigma^{-1}\sigma = e_A = \sigma\sigma^{-1}.</m>
            </p>
        </statement>
    </theorem>

    <remark>
        <statement>
            <p>
                We need to note that composition is <em>not commutative</em>. Generally speaking, <m>\sigma\tau\neq\tau\sigma</m>. To demonstrate, observe
            </p>
            <image source="./images/perm_prod_ex2.svg" />
            <p>
                Clearly <m>gh\neq hg</m>, since two permutations can only be equal if they agree on every point in the domain.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </remark>

    <p>
        Composition of permutations satisfies another desirable property: it is associative. That is, <m>\sigma(\tau\phi) = (\sigma\tau)\phi</m>.
    </p>
    <definition>
        <statement>
            <p>
                A <term>group</term> is a set <m>G</m> along with an associative operation <m>*</m> which has an identity element and for which each element <m>g\in G</m> has a unique inverse <m>g^{-1}\in G</m>. The set <m>S_A</m> with composition is thus called the <term>symmetric group over <m>A</m></term>.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>

    <remark>
        <p>
            In fact, the study of group theory (which begins for modern students in Abstract Algebra) was inspired by the work of Lagrange on generalizations of permutation groups. An important result in group theory, especially for those working with groups in an applied setting, is <em>Cayley's Theorem</em>.
        </p>
    </remark>
    <theorem>
        <title>Cayley's Theorem</title>
        <statement>
            Every abstract group is isomorphic<fn>An <term>isomorphism</term> is a property-preserving bijection. In the context of groups, <m>\phi:G\to H</m> is an isomorphism if and only if it is a bijection and <m>\phi(g_1\cdot g_2)=\phi(g_1)\cdot\phi(g_2)</m> for every <m>g_1,g_2\in G</m>.</fn> to a subgroup of a symmetric group.
        </statement>
    </theorem>
</section>
