<section>
<title>Pivoting strategies</title>


<introduction>
<p>
A <em>pivoting strategy</em> is an algorithm which decides when to interchange rows (and/or columns) to avoid errors such as swamping.
</p>
</introduction>


<subsection>
<title>Partial pivoting</title>
<p>
In partial pivoting, we consider the magnitude of elements in the column before selecting a pivot element. The unpivoted row containing an element of maximum magnitude in a column is first swapped with the pivot row, and then the elimination step for that row proceeds. Consider the augmented matrix in <xref ref="eq_aug" autoname="yes" /> once again. In each step, the column entry of maximum magnitude is underlined for easy location, and then (if necessary) swapped into the correct location. Once the <q>largest</q> element is in the pivot position, we'll use the elimination step of sending all column values beneath the pivot to 0.
<md>
  <mrow>  \left[\begin{array}{3} 1 \amp  3 \amp  -13 \amp  -18 \\ 1 \amp  2 \amp  -10 \amp  -15\\ \mathbf{\underline{-6}} \amp  -7 \amp  46 \amp  77
\end{array} \right]
	\xto{R_1:R_3}
	\amp \left[\begin{array}{3} -6 \amp  -7 \amp  46 \amp  77 \\ 1 \amp  2 \amp  -10 \amp  -15 \\ 1 \amp  3 \amp  -13 \amp  -18
\end{array} \right]
	\xrightarrow[\frac16 R_1+R_3]{\frac16R_1+R_2}
	\left[\begin{array}{3} 
		-6 \amp  -7 \amp  46 \amp  77 \\ 
		0 \amp  \frac56 \amp  -\frac73 \amp  -\frac{13}6 \\
		0 \amp  \mathbf{\underline{\frac{11}6}} \amp  -\frac{16}3 \amp  -\frac{31}6
\end{array} \right]</mrow>
  <mrow>  \xto{R_2:R_3}
	\amp \left[\begin{array}{3}
		-6 \amp  -7 \amp  46 \amp  77 \\ 
		0 \amp  \frac{11}6 \amp  -\frac{16}3 \amp  -\frac{31}6\\
		0 \amp  \frac56 \amp  -\frac73 \amp  -\frac{13}6
\end{array} \right]
	\xto{-\frac5{11}R_2+R_3}
	\left[\begin{array}{3}
		-6 \amp  -7 \amp  46 \amp  77 \\ 
		0 \amp  \frac{11}6 \amp  -\frac{16}3 \amp  -\frac{31}6\\
		0 \amp  0 \amp  \frac1{11} \amp  \frac2{11}
\end{array} \right]</mrow>
</md>
</p>

<p>
}
Following up with back substitution,
<md>
  <mrow>  x_3 = \frac{2/11}{1/11} \amp = 2,</mrow>
  <mrow>  x_2 = \frac6{11}\left(-\frac{31}6+\frac{16}3x_3\right) \amp = 3,</mrow>
  <mrow>  x_1 = -\frac16\left(77+7x_2_46x_3\right) \amp = -1</mrow>
</md>
</p>

<p>
In this example, we see no net gain; in the example with swamping, we will.
</p>

<example>
<statement>
<p>
Recall our swamping example. This time we'll use floating-point arithmetic but include partial pivoting.
<md>
  <mrow>  \begin{abmc}{2}10.0^{-20} \amp  1.0 \amp  1.0</mrow>
  <mrow>  1.0 \amp  2.0 \amp  4.0\end{abmc} 
	\xto{R_1:R_2}
	\amp \begin{abmc}{2}
		1.0 \amp  2.0 \amp  4.0</mrow>
  <mrow>  10.0^{-20} \amp  1.0 \amp  1.0
	\end{abmc}
	\xto{-10.0^{-20}R_1+R_2}
	\left[\begin{array}{2}
		1.0 \amp  2.0 \amp  4.0 \\
		0.0 \amp  1.0 \amp  1.0
\end{array} \right]</mrow>
</md>
</p>

<p>
Back substitution is immediate:
<md>
  <mrow>  x_2 \amp = 1.0,</mrow>
  <mrow>  x_1 = 4.0 - 2.0x_2 \amp = 2.0.</mrow>
</md>
</p>

<p>
So we see that using partial pivoting totally avoided the error. The small difference which occurred and was ignored did so in the correct level of significance, and the actual difference between the correct answer and its floating point approximation is below the level of precision of floating point arithmetic!
</p>
</statement>
</example>
</subsection>


<subsection>
<title>Complete Pivoting</title>
<p>
Complete pivoting involves swapping the columns as well as the rows, which is slightly dangerous <mdash /> this changes the order of the solutions. An interesting way to track these changes is to use a <em>permutation matrix</em>. Suppose that <m>A</m> is a <m>m\times n</m> matrix, and <m>I</m> is the <m>n\times n</m> identity matrix. Then if <m>A'</m> and <m>I'</m> are the results of swapping the <m>i^\text{ th }</m> and <m>j^\text{ th }</m> columns in both <m>A</m> and <m>I</m>, it is the case that
<me>
  A = AI = A'I'.
</me>
</p>

<p>
Hence a sequence of column swaps on <m>A</m> can be tracked by making the same sequence of column swaps on an identity matrix <m>I</m> of the correct dimensions.
</p>

<p>
The pivot selection for complete pivoting is to swap the largest-magnitude entry in the submatrix below and to the right of the previous pivot point into the current pivot position via a row and column swap.
</p>
</subsection>

</section>
